<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Reflections | Vladimir Tsvetkov]]></title>
  <link href="http://npacemo.github.io/blog/categories/reflections/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://npacemo.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-15T11:24:29+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://npacemo.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vladimir Tsvetkov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Return to the Habit of Recording and Sharing What I Learn]]></title>
    <link href="http://npacemo.github.io/blog/2014/01/04/return-to-the-habit-of-recording-and-sharing-what-i-learn/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-04T12:44:42+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://npacemo.github.io/blog/2014/01/04/return-to-the-habit-of-recording-and-sharing-what-i-learn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During my Christmas vacation I was spending some time thinking about and exploring ways how to inspire my team at <a href="http://www.obecto.com/" title="Obecto - Boutique Software Development Company">Obecto</a> to expand its learning bandwidth. This has led me somehow to the <a href="http://manifesto.softwarecraftsmanship.org/#/en" title="Manifesto for Software Craftsmanship">Software Craftsmanship Manifesto</a> and then to the <a href="http://manifesto.softwarecraftsmanship.org/#/en/reading" title="Software Craftsmanship - Background Materials">Further Reading Materials</a> where I have found the online version of the <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/index.html" title="Apprenticeship Patterns">Apprenticeship Patterns Book</a>. This book has caught my attention right from the start and in the next few days I felt the necessity to read the whole book.</p>

<p>Reading it led me to inspiration <em>(one result of that is me spending the last 2 days of my vacation to setup and start this blog, and also writing this article)</em> and many ideas about initiatives and ways to approach the learning process within my team. But more importantly, it helped me reignite and start <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/ch03.html#nurture_your_passion" title="Apprenticeship Patterns &gt; Chapter 3 &gt; Nurture Your Passion">nurturing my passion</a> for the craft again. It led me to some important reflections and it reminded me about my <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/ch03.html#the_long_road" title="Apprenticeship Patterns &gt; Chapter 3 &gt; The Long Road">long road</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Important reflections and realizations</h2>

<ol>
<li><strong>I need to regain the <em>sense of control</em> and responsibility for my learning process.</strong> It&rsquo;s not that I&rsquo;m not doing any learning&hellip; Looking at 2013 in retrospect, I&rsquo;ve been involved in quite a lot of learning activities. I attended a <a href="http://fmi.clojure.bg/" title="Programming in Clojure">Clojure programming</a> course at the Sofia University. I didn&rsquo;t finished the course, but managed to pull it through the 60% of the course curriculum and home work assignments. Roughly, at the same time I&rsquo;ve enrolled the <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/progfun" title="Functional Programming Principles in Scala | Coursera">Functional Programming Principles in Scala</a> course at <a href="https://www.coursera.org/" title="Coursera">Coursera</a>. Again and sadly, I didn&rsquo;t finished the course and I haven&rsquo;t submitted the Week 6 and Week 7 assignments on time. I realise now that both of these learning efforts were not-that-well-thought-through attempts to <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/ch05.html#expand_your_bandwidth" title="Apprenticeship Patterns &gt; Chapter 5 &gt; Expand Your Bandwidth">expand my bandwidth</a>. Both of them failed because they didn&rsquo;t fit into a <strong>sustainable learning strategy</strong> that was considering realistically how much time and energy I&rsquo;m investing in my companies. My projects at that time entered a phase that required 110% of my attention and I had to assign low priority to my learning activities&hellip; And this is how my <em>deliberate learning</em> for 2013 just ceased. Both my Clojure and Scala skills now would take some considerable time to recover. But again recovering those would be in vain if I don&rsquo;t spend some time to <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/ch03.html#draw_your_own_map" title="Apprenticeship Patterns &gt; Chapter 3 &gt; Draw Your Own Map">draw my own map</a> and see where does, for example, the skill of Clojure programming fits into my overall career strategy. The <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/index.html" title="Apprenticeship Patterns">Apprenticeship Patterns Book</a> helped me realize that from now I should strive not just to spend time on learning new and interesting stuff, but rather approach learning in a way more systematic fashion by implementing a whole micro-architecture of related learning patterns,  supporting practices and even habits.</li>
<li><strong>Lots of reusable and transferable knowledge I&rsquo;ve lost unrecorded.</strong> I have lost the count of how many times I&rsquo;ve decided that there&rsquo;s no time to record a lessons I&rsquo;ve learned. And later I run repeatedly into a situation where I have to either learn the same lesson again or I have to recollect the details of a solution by digging really deep into my faded memories. Sometimes it is something as small as a specific shell command that is useful in a certain situation, but sometimes it is something bigger such as a non-obvious architectural solution that takes into consideration a number of undocumented technical constraints. In all of these situations I have to invest a lot of effort. I feel especially bad when I recall <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?LarryWall" title="Larry Wall">Larry Wall</a> who encourages every programmer to develop the <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?LazinessImpatienceHubris" title="Laziness Impatience Hubris">three great virtues</a> of our craft: <em>laziness, impatience, and hubris</em>. He says about <strong><em>laziness</em></strong>, <em>&ldquo;that this is the quality that makes you go to great effort to reduce overall energy expenditure. It makes you write labor-saving programs that other people will find useful, and document what you wrote so you don&rsquo;t have to answer so many questions about it. Hence, the first great virtue of a programmer.&rdquo;</em> It&rsquo;s unrealistic to expect that I&rsquo;ll be able to record absolutely all lessons I&rsquo;m learning in my everyday work, but now I&rsquo;m determined to record as much as I can. Hacking this blog together is a step forwards in the way of achieving this goal. I used to have a blog, you know, with articles mostly on <em>Flash and Flex</em> <em>(which is no longer accessible &ndash; <a href="http://npacemo.com/">http://npacemo.com/</a>)</em>, and it was popular enough for me to feel that I&rsquo;m doing a decent job with it. Gradually I was writing less and less frequently, until I totally stopped and the content in my blog eventually became irrelevant. My point is <em>if I fail to form the habit of <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/ch05.html#record_what_you_learn" title="Apprenticeship Patterns &gt; Chapter 5 &gt; Record What You Learn">recording what you learn</a></em> this blog will most likely fall into the steps of my former one. Currently, I&rsquo;m learning more and more about habit formation and this gives me a bit more confidence.</li>
<li><strong>Taking a <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/ch03.html#a_different_road" title="Apprenticeship Patterns &gt; Chapter 3 &gt; A Different Road">different road</a> doesn&rsquo;t mean I&rsquo;ve lost <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/ch03.html#the_long_road" title="Apprenticeship Patterns &gt; Chapter 3 &gt; The Long Road">my long road</a>.</strong> My <em>long road</em> was and I believe it is still all about the <strong><em>software development</em></strong> part of bringing a software product or service to life. The steps that I have taken so far were quite focused on gaining the special skills needed to become a <em>great programmer</em>. No matter what role(s) and responsibilities I was exercising in my projects I was always capable <em>(and probably I still am)</em> to switch to <em>programming mode</em>, to get into this flow and be able to put to the deepest corner of my head the fact that I&rsquo;m also a <em>VP Engineering</em> for <a href="http://www.obecto.com/" title="Obecto - Boutique Software Development Company">my company</a>. Now when the company has grown over a certain number of team members, customers and projects, I realize that switching into <em>programming mode</em> would not only be very hard for me <em>(because I need to cope with this variety of different attitudes and modes of behavior)</em>, but it would also harm the growth of my company. Now is the time for me to focus 100% on <em>the tasks of platform selection, technical design and optimizing the development processes for this selection and technology choices, managing the process of organizing and synchronizing the requirements, managing the teams, properly allocating people, growing team leaders and technical leaders, and make sure all projects succeed in execution</em>. In short, I need to totally own the <strong><em>development methodology</em></strong> instead of showing off my programming skills. At a later stage, I&rsquo;m pretty sure I&rsquo;ll get back to the craft of programming and even become a better programmer than I have ever been, but for now I&rsquo;m on a <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/ch03.html#a_different_road" title="Apprenticeship Patterns &gt; Chapter 3 &gt; A Different Road">different road</a>.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Next steps</h2>

<ol>
<li><strong>Present the ideas from <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/index.html" title="Apprenticeship Patterns">Apprenticeship Patterns</a> to my team.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Continue to <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001813/ch05.html#record_what_you_learn" title="Apprenticeship Patterns &gt; Chapter 5 &gt; Record What You Learn">record what I learn</a> in this blog, in my company Wiki and in the projects Wikis, and in my analog journal, and try to turn this into a habit.</strong></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
